[SPEAKER_00]: So, Bhante, I'm facing a dilemma.
[SPEAKER_00]: My parents want me to pursue a family and a successful business, believing it will bring happiness and merit for the both of us.
[SPEAKER_00]: However, I see this as unbeneficial in the context of saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I choose monastic life, I'll disobey my parents and hurt them, as they don't value the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there a way to avoid causing them pain while following my path?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, you can't have it both ways.
[SPEAKER_01]: On one hand, you have, you have a goal that's kind of easier to accomplish in a way, more palpable, more satisfactory to more people, get your family, job, look after parents.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the other hand, but then, you know, it has its limited benefits.
[SPEAKER_01]: Benefits are kind of, up to this life, and even that's questionable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not guaranteed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not guaranteed that you'll be sickness-free and aging and death.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's unavoidable and it might come sooner than expected.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, plus lots of other factors can come in the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the other hand, you have a task that would
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, displease everybody around you, be much harder to accomplish, much more uncertain to succeed at, but if you do, then you're done.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have ended the saṃsāra for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just like how, what type of vision you have, whether it's short-sighted or long-sighted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you courageous enough or not?
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't go both ways.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also, if you think like, oh, well, you know, I'll do one for a bit, then I'll do the other one later, theoretically, I suppose that's possible, but practically, the longer you stay engaging with a household life, household duties, accumulating results of the actions of a householder, the more burden is accumulated, which means it's going to be harder and harder to give it up, because it's... the more time it passes, it's going to start to concern more and more people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just you and your parents.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it will be factually harder to to sever those ties.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not a... it's not a... it's not the status quo.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not... it's not going to stay a neutral thing, that then you can just switch 20 years from now on.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: The burden will be there, binding you even harder.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to be... basically, you want to make that decision sooner, rather than later, and then stick to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we come up with this kind of... meet many people that come up with this dilemma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it was in the suttas often as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, parents leaving the family.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want to harm the parents.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you think, do they know what is beneficial?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, see, back in India,
[SPEAKER_01]: You leave your family, if you were the only son, there was a good chance they probably won't live much longer, or when they reach the old age, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were their insurance policy, but that's not the case today.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you might displease them, but hardly parents today would be existentially threatened if their child leaves, certainly if you come from the Western society.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, there is plenty of systems in order that you wouldn't need.
[SPEAKER_01]: And mind you, even people whose children don't leave them, they're not, you know, the children don't look after the parents.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just not...
[SPEAKER_01]: There's so many other ways.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, then you want to also... just check, basically, is it just that you're going to cause the mental discomfort and upset and disappointment?
[SPEAKER_01]: And don't conflate that with like, oh, no, they really need me for their survival, which is most likely not the case.
[SPEAKER_01]: But either way, you're gonna have to take responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you choose to appease to them, you can't then, later on in your life, complain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you chose what they wanted over what you wanted.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have to stick to that now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And everything that comes out of it, twenty years later, it's on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't blame your parents or anybody.
[SPEAKER_01]: You made that choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same, if you choose to pursue the way out of saṃsāra and go the uncertain path, build up the courage, it's on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any suffering that your parents have, upset, disappointment, it's on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you can't... you have to accept it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, again, if you practice successfully, you will find a way out of it without needing to abandon your practice in the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: But,
[SPEAKER_01]: That is conditional upon successful practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could use it as an inspiration and a criteria and a threshold for the successfulness of your practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, are you able to bear the weight of leaving your parents, incurring them suffering, to do what you want, not doing what they want from you, despite them raising you, investing their whole life in you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you able to endure that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Practice rightly, not be moved by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, each time you get careless in your practice, just remember what's at stake.
[SPEAKER_01]: The welfare of your parents that you abandoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can you afford then to be careless and mess around and, oh, today I'll ignore my intentions and I'll act out of sensuality?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because this is what you caused.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's quite interesting, because you can use that remembering
[SPEAKER_00]: If your parents are hurt by your going forth, you can use that as a motivation to do the right thing, which is actually the right thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which could lead, in the future then, to you... if you had to succeed even just a little bit, being virtuous and then finding peace in that and...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that is the most meritorious for them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, if you had to... your parents had to then meet you again, at that point, and they were good enough parents, they would at least recognize that their son, their daughter was actually happy, actually doing quite well.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that would then make them happy as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if he doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be worth it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if he doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that they would have raised a being, an individual, that has now
[SPEAKER_01]: Become established in virtue and right view and efforts and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will partake in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you wouldn't be where you were if they haven't raised you rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's I mean, it's beneficial for them as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, it's... they might not see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yeah, it's good if you have compassion for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is an opening for them to hear it, to learn from you, which there might be, and it's probably a good likelihood, you know, if sometimes they pass, they'll come around and accept that and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But either way, it's not going to be easy.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you choose to stay because it feels like, oh, you're going to appease more people sooner and it feels safer, is it though?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you might not see tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what... what have you... Basically, you gave up the whole opportunity for a complete freedom and escape on account of something that... that you didn't even get to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, people do assume they're going to live forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when they make these plans about the future and family and job and looking after parents, the years, decades ahead, it's like...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but do you have that much time?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you even know that?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you were to think more acutely, in a more disciplined manner of your situation, that liability to sickness, aging and death is not 30 years from now on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always the same, always equal from the day you were born.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you would...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it would be easier to make this decision.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would not... you would not... you would not even be considering, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would not be weighing these options.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, one, not just that it's even more uncertain, but you might not even get to actually develop it the way you were hoping.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you had to have the perspective of what you just said, death all the time is there for you, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you have that perspective, well, if you have that perspective and then the world is telling you that you're wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, that's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing can come in between that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, just experience that anxiety of things could end.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter who says what.
[SPEAKER_01]: It won't make a difference to that recognition.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's when you yourself forget it, or think you're kind of absolved from it, that's when you start considering these long-term things, and forgetting how uncertain they actually are, and how contingent they are upon all sorts of things that are not in your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your health, other people's health, circumstances, everything else around you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not sure about your perspective that you have, that death is always present.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not sure about that, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the world starts to say to you, no, that's not the way it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Forget it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it hasn't sunk in.
[SPEAKER_00]: It hasn't sunk in then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're swayed still by the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I mean, even asking a question, or can I have both?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can I do both?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's already like...
[SPEAKER_01]: You know the answer there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're just hoping, reaching for straws, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to hear something magical that will absorb you from responsibility either way.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I'm saying the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're going to accept responsibility for both.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you stay with your parents, you have to accept responsibility for everything that comes out of it, and for not pursuing the practice and liberating yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you go and pursue the practice for liberating yourself, you have to accept the full responsibility for that,
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever you're slacking, non-diligent, lazy, you're gonna accept that and the fact that you cause your parents immense amount of pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not just that you can't have both, you're gonna have even less either way.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that is still more right than lying to yourself about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you become a monk, then your responsibility, not just that it doesn't diminish, it doubles up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's a good thing.